part of my job is not to make
presumptions but it is to ask the
question or at least to place the
question out there why is that and a big
part of that is really some of the ideas
around hiring in one's own image I
wouldn't so much say is that they don't
have the key I guess is the kind of
Social and cultural
capital that one can amass from being in
those situations now there is a
membership to that kind of social
cultural capital I think the social and
kind of human mechanism that play
is an intrinsic one and there are
reasons intrinsically why somebody's
motivated to want to help someone my
wish and my dream and all of my
Endeavors have always worked towards
everybody being able to swim in this
ocean as opposed to a few people being
able to swim in this
ocean hi everyone thank you for joining
us today for this new episode of the
diversity seminar
as usual we're going to have a wonderful
conversation with one person that is a
leader of diversity in Europe and as you
know also this initiative is completely
nonprofit so the only goal is to inspire
young diverse professionals provide them
with ideas insights and tips also to get
better in the corporate world
[Music]
so I've been in the corporate work for
35 years in executive positions worked
across Europe traveled extensively
across Europe worked with many teams
across Europe met many companies across
Ross Europe and so I decided to have
those interviews with person that really
have an impact on the diversity Topic in
Europe one year ago I started this
initiative and I met amazing CEOs and
you've seen the previous podcast with
amazing CEOs leaders of diversity in
Europe but I thought it would be
interesting to step back and think of
what is happening what are the
structural things happening in the
corporate world and what is happening in
society when it comes to diversity in
the corporate world and so I asked many
leaders who can I meet to have a
conversation about what's happening in
society when it comes to diversity and
they all mentioned to me you must meet a
wonderful scholar from Cambridge named
Jason so I was introduced to Jason and
he immediately accepted and so today I'm
so glad and so honored to have this time
with Jason ay so Jason thank you so much
for your time today I really appreciate
that no no not at all Max it's such a
privilege to be here and thank you so so
much for having me here so Jason just to
um introduce quickly um because you have
a pretty incredible story I'll I'll ask
you maybe to to share with us in a few
minutes a bit about your personal story
but for for now you're one of the
youngest professor at
Oxbridge uh you have a chair of
Sociology in Cambridge if I understand
well yes and you're very specialized
about everything that relates to
Sociology when it comes to ethnicity
race when it comes to education when it
comes to um mental health when it comes
also to social origin is that is that
correct yeah that's yeah that's that's
pretty much the nail on the head Max um
so a lot of the work I do is really
through an intersectional lens um which
kind of covers the Gambit of areas in
terms of understanding some of the some
of the kind of complexities of race and
racism across several different insects
like class gender sexuality disability
Etc so that's that's a lot of what I do
and really kind of make some sense
around how we can disrupt some of those
systemic and institutional problems and
recommendations for how we can move
forward as a collective Society
fantastic fantastic so listen we we're
going to have this conversation if few
minut but first of all I would like you
to share a bit if you're okay with that
about your own personal story because I
must say it's absolutely mindblowing and
for example I understand
that if I'm not indiscrete that you were
not speaking until you were 11 years old
and you started reading at 18 years old
which seems absolutely incredible could
you share a bit about your personal
story yeah so um I mean I think most
people around the world know this now so
if I'm boring someone at nauseum um it's
not because I've told everyone it's
because it's kind of just reverberated
um but the the kind of the key numbers
are 3 11 18 and 37 so I was diagnosed
with autism
in old money Asperia syndrome um which
you wouldn't use that term now at all
when I was three and Global development
DeLay So this affects kind of there's a
cognitive impairment with that um which
means that when you're supposed to
approach certain milestones
cognitively in those days they kept they
kind of encapsulated it by saying
intellectually you didn't reach those
Milestones um I as a consequence I
couldn't speak until I was 11 um which
was
which to me wasn't a disadvantage in the
way people may think so when people
think of disability they often think
through the medical model of disability
which is disabling you know um and I
guess the social model of disability
really focuses on the ability aspect so
I I never and this is thanks to my mom
by the way so I I never there wasn't a
sense of feeling like I was at a
disadvantage because it allowed me to
observe human beings
in quite a fortunate way you know um the
the Stillness of speech the paralysis of
speech in some respects you get to
observe human beings and those
interactions and it's it's probably not
a coincidence that of all the things I
ended up doing I I effectively talk for
a living so if was an IR that would be
it and when I was 18 learned to read and
write because as a consequence of the
global development delay you kind of you
know a lot of those processes meant that
I was able kind of make sense of those
things a lot later than I should have
done which is quite normal for people
with global development Delay from 18 I
learned to read and write I was very
fortunate that um you know all the kind
of cogs came together and I was able to
kind of make sense all the early Embers
of making sense of being able to read
and write um and that was obviously
flanked I was flanked by a fantastic
tutor I had at College at the time
called sandre sandre this kind of crazy
Italian Brazilian who took me under his
wing and really kind of propelled my
learning in that area and then I guess
the kind of num that of of more
consequence is probably 37 so I I became
a professor at Cambridge when I was 37
but I actually got my first
professorship when I was 35 so that was
um when I was at University of Glasgow
and at that point it made me the
youngest professor in the UK um and then
I was very fortunate that the uh rest
happened and and I guess that's history
so everyone knows how that turned out
but I I I think look all that Glitters
Is Not Gold and I think sometimes what
people see is the veneer of the end
product there's a lot of things that
happen in between and that happen along
the journey there's a lot of people who
make a lot of sacrifice for that to
happen namely my mom gifty who was
instrumental and Sandro who had
dedicated you know I've known him since
I was 18 and I'm 39 now so he dedicated
the larger part of his adult life
towards helping me um achieve my my
goals so I've been very very fortunate
in that regard um and that's something
that I I often hold dear and try and sit
in that kind of humility
because lots of people work hard and
they're not always fortunate to get what
they deserve out of life and um I did
work hard but I've been very very
fortunate to have been able to get some
change out of life and I do feel very
fortunate for that it's um it's a very
touching story and um I I knew about the
story of course because we discussed and
that also did my my own my home work
right um but I find that so
inspirational you know how to and look
look at you now yeah you know it's funny
because I guess you know there's a lot
of times where you sit down and you
think what I always think about is how
different things could have
been so there's two things I don't place
all the worth in value in being a
Cambridge Professor because ultimately
it's not everything the thing that are
of Greater
meaning is the fact that I'm very
fortunate to wake up and do something
that I I feel very blessed to be able to
do I I also know how difficult life can
be for many people including
myself and you know part of that part of
those experiences that I had on my way
to getting to that point give me at
least a balanced perspective on what is
important and what isn't important and
it's not you know I'm not trivializing
the Cambridge Post by any stretch the
imagination but it's not everything
doesn't affect the person who's who's
suffering um on the street it doesn't
affect the person who is living below
the breadline those you know those
things the title and of itself and the
post you know one could argue as
ceremonial but a lot of the things that
I'm invested in are really about how we
can mobilize and help the greater good
that's always been the mission and no
book or paper that I have a right is
going to help people in those situations
but what does help people are my actions
and the things that I do outside of
Academia and that's more poignant and
more pertinent to me in terms of
actually having some small effect on
people's everyday lives which is
remarkable and um I know you're very
humble but um I know that you're having
such a huge impact on many Charities
across the UK and you're working closely
with many Charities and and doing very
tangible things to support them which is
absolutely amazing so I'm so I'm so
inspired by that it's very kind of you
thank you so let's um transition into
the the topic of the corporate world
yeah and I really wanted to have this
conversation with you and I'm so
thankful to you that we have this
conversation because I always thought
that the corporate world is just a
subset of society and so what happens in
society kind of interacts with what's
happening in the corporate world and I
wanted to get some more perspective some
more depth about the mechanism of what's
happening in the corporate world so in
35 years I've seen amazing progress made
when it comes to gender diversity in the
corporate world it's not perfect far
from that but the progress are
phenomenal and I've seen that from the
internal of the companies I've seen the
push and the drive for that when I see
at the same time what happened with
ethnic
diversity progress are less clear okay
so I wondered why is that what's what's
happening behind that okay and so the
first thing I'm always hearing I hear
the story that well diverse young
talents are difficult to find in the
marketplace and I must say it's bizarre
so any any take on that I think
familiarity is is quite an interesting
concept when we think about
organizations and structures and a big
part of that is really some of the ideas
around hiring in one's own
image and part of that is we look at
these kind of workspaces and their
microcosm of society and very often it
depends what that Society is to the
individuals that may be the the power
Brokers or the stakeholders in that
organization now if those individuals
are exposed to diverse ranges of people
that in a sense Pricks something in
one's conscience to think about how
useful will a diverse Workforce be if
individuals aren't exposed to that and
by proxy their world is quite narrow in
that sense it can limit the range of
people that they bring into those
organizations which is why you can have
these homogeneous organizations which
have you know which are predom
predominantly white if we're talking
about huge executive
companies and in terms of thinking about
that opportunity it tends to often be
reactive in response to a particular
phenomena so let's take the most recent
vintage black lives matter movement in
2020 there was a huge kind
of rear guard action and response by
organizations to think about how they
diversify things um but what has been
interesting about that
is we're kind of four years away from
that and actually a lot of those
organizations have slipped back into
patterns of replicating that familiarity
in terms of the types of people they
have in those
organizations
so I do think it's an interesting
phenomena because the truth
is there has to be an appetite to want
to diversify and to want to change and I
guess the question that I would place at
the center of this discussion would be
do those individuals have the appetite
to want to do that because
familiarity and unconscious biases they
do play a huge part in recruit in
Recruitment and recruiting processes and
the types of individuals are afforded
such opportunities so when we kind of
look across the intersection and we look
at where advancements have been made we
spoke about gender but when we talk
about gender let's be really really
specific what types of individuals are
being given those opportunities because
I think I could make a
reasonably
educated argument that it isn't women of
color to be honest and I don't say that
without any hesitation I say that
because I'm always mindful of the kind
of backlash that people have towards
hearing these things but it's very
important not to caveat these things not
to kind of provide and and just to say
what the situation is which is that you
know if we're talking about gender
advancement as just one example you
know who who has benefited from that
gender advancement and so the question
in some respects it's an open question
it's not a rhetorical question it's an
open question because you always want
people to fill the blanks with that you
know in in the sense that your eyes
don't lie to you so if my eyes are lying
to me then I I would like someone to
provide me with what the truth is
because I don't think my eyes lie to me
so I can as an observational exercise
given that I had 11 years to just
observe human beings without without
speech I think I'm well informed I'm
informed enough to be able to make that
assessment and I think it is interesting
that we don't see there is an absence of
diversification in large
organizations but I I think there are
lots of people that will have a lot of
reasons as to why that is the case and
sometimes those reasons don't actually
deal with the Crux of the problem and
the Crux of the problem
is why is there an absence of diversity
in organizations when they focus their
efforts whether it be
fiscal or any other kind of
resource why are elements of diversity
and let's be really specific and drill
down
race peripheral considerations you know
they don't occupy the organizational
center it's not an organizational
priority but but why is that you know
and part of my job is not to make
presumption but it is to ask the
question or at least to place the
question out there why is that now I I
could surmise and I have many reasons as
to why I think that
is but again it comes down to this IDE
of
familiarity which is such an important
top which which is a huge important
thing you know and and that familiarity
really kind of encapsulates what is in
many cases an unchallenged unconscious
bias about the types of individuals you
have in an organization because it's not
a coincidence in big organizations that
you have the same types of people occupy
the same types of spaces that is not by
coincidence that is by Design but what I
do believe is that you can unconsciously
unpack that by Design aspect of one's
psyche and get them to think in more
broader terms about why it's important
to have diversity in an organization not
just within the context of race but
across the the intersection more broadly
totally and you know it's it's
fascinating what you're saying here
because um first of all I absolutely do
not buy the idea that we can't find
talents out there I absolutely do buy
that there's so many wonderful talents
from very various type of diversities
out there and they are so capable and
they just want to succeed and they just
want to contribute to society and to
Corporation so I just don't buy that and
then there's something very interesting
that I've noticed is that in fact
companies tried to bring some diversity
and sometime succeeded sometimes succeed
less but they they tried and what is
very interesting is that when I think of
ethnic diversity
typically there's there's a wave of more
professionals joining corporations which
is good but they tend to stay at the
lowest level of the companies okay so
when I was looking at first line manages
second line manures there were way less
of ethnically diverse um
professionals when I was looking at
applied
management very seldom and when I was
looking at GM roles um ex ex commit
roles or even Coo's rle then literally
none and so it is it's a bit bizarre and
also interesting right to to have this
situation does it relat also to
familiarity or is there something else
Happening Here I I think again it comes
back to this word of familiarity and
design you know why are those
individuals of black and ethnic minority
backgrounds why do they reside in the
lower echelons and Chambers of an
organization
um I think the counter to that argument
is always this idea around a lack of
ambition
so there's always this thing that black
and ethnic minority people they lack
ambition
and obviously I I completely do not
subscribe to that I think there are also
not clear Pathways for black and ethnic
minority people to progress in
organizations
because in many respects the progression
opportunities are few and far between
and there is also this positioning of
particular groups of people not being
capable or not being seen as capable by
organizations and it is problematic
because again it goes back to this
familiarity of what is how do we Define
Excellence how do we Define kind of prer
career progression and what does that
look like for particular groups of
individuals and I think that because
there isn't a firm blueprint for black
and ethnic minority people and just
generally speaking in in most
organizations it makes it very hard for
them to Traverse
and know understand the Rules of
Engagement because the Rules of
Engagement in some respects are like
shifting Sands so tur there's a
turbulence there in that they change
very frequently for black and ethnic
minority people in a way that they don't
for other ethnic groups that's so
interesting that's so interesting and
I'm I'm thinking here that um on the
topic of ambition for example that you
mentioned so I worked with many many
young Professionals of all
ethnicities and I've I've mentored like
I don't know 40 young talented
professionals from ethnic
minorities I've never ever seen them
lacking ambition never they all have
tons of ambition they all want to
succeed and they can be black they can
be Arabs they can be Asians they can be
Indians whatever okay they all want to
succeed they want they all want you to
impact um have a great career and uh I
never I've never noticed a lack of
ambition but what I've noticed in the
corporate world is that quite often
young professionals from diverse origin
and by the way the social origin plays a
very powerful component into that too so
it can be across the notion of all other
diversities right but what I've not this
is that a lot of young professionals
they they don't really feel comfortable
it it feels like they don't have
the the understanding or they don't have
the the keys to operate in this
environment and they don't feel really
comfortable is that is that is there a
reason for that do you see an analysis
behind that yeah I mean I wouldn't so
much say is that they don't have the key
I guess is the kind of Social and
cultural
capital that one can amass from being in
those situations now there is a
membership to that kind of social
cultural
capital um something as simple as being
invited to events outside of work which
types of people are invited to those
events you know that that there are
exclusionary processes that happen in
organizations which mean that the access
to Capital and to information that helps
a person Traverse an organization or
advanc an
organization there's an exclusivity to
that club it's an exclusivity to the
individuals who are able to gain
membership and access to this
information there's there's an invisible
subscription that people pay and very
often that subscription isn't offered in
a compulsory or voluntary way you know
it's a given to a particular type of
individual a particular type of person
and seldom is that a black or an ethnic
minority person and so very often
they're for they're foraging and and
trying to find a way to mobilize themsel
in those organizations but it becomes
very difficult without a compass and I
guess in these
organizations what people of color are
very often not given is a compass to
navigate these
organizations in comparison to their
white counterparts who are often given
the compasses to be able to navigate
these
organizations and and when you when you
mentioned
blueprint could you forge a out what
what blueprint could looks like what are
the key components of blueprints yeah I
mean if we was going to kind of use it
as
a as a kind of translatable kind of
context across any organization when I
talk about the term blueprint it's
almost like an ingred it's almost like a
set of ingredients so how do you bake a
cake I want to know that when I bake a
cake I can take that recipe and I and I
can do this thing you know 100 times and
yeah the cake might not turn out the
same but the fundamental principles are
there you know I do this I do this I do
this I do this I have a cake voila and I
guess what I'm saying is that those set
of
ingredients they change they're very
interchangeable when it comes for people
when it comes to people of color trying
to bake a cake so that cake might be my
professional career and I kind of want
to know that it's going to look the same
as my white counterpart but because of
those intersectional variables that are
at play it's not likely that that will
be the case and so when we talk about
this road map it's a case of the idea of
meritocracy is a great it's great in
theory but in actual
practice it
falls time and time and time again
because meritocracy in itself is not
equal there is no equity in meritocracy
only a small proportion or certain group
of people from society benefit from
meritocracy when you bring in those
other intersectional
factors a lot of people don't benefit
from meritocracy and in terms of that
road map what I want to know is if let's
just say any individual that wanted to
become a CEO of a
company what is the blueprint to doing
that what do I have to do in an
organization to ascend to the top and
I'm not saying that it should be
straightforward but it should be a
pretty consistent road map in terms of
you do this you do this you do this you
do this and you might be lucky what I
don't believe or what I think is a
problem is that an individual can pay
the on those things and then there are
aspects intersectionally like their
sexuality or their gender or their class
or their race or their disability or
their religion that might compromise
their ability to kind of climb or Ascend
on that ladder to um Chief to being a
chief executive officer so that's that's
always been my issue why does it not
affect some people and why does it
affect a particular group of people and
again it's one of those kind of
open-ended questions that I think is
always interesting for people to think
about and consider given some of the
dominant discourses that exist around
why people don't become you know mobile
upwardly mobile in an
organization and I say that because I I
don't want to make the presumption that
everything I'm saying is correct but I
do want people to use their eyes as I
mentioned earlier because your eyes
don't lie to you and kind of question
why are things the way they are and they
may have a log IAL rationale for why
that is but I would say you know part of
it is really challenging those values
and belief systems and thinking about
actually why if we live in a
multicultural multi-ethnic multi-
diverse Society we have huge
organizations that
feed that support that are for the
province of a greater and wider Society
why don't we have organizations that are
reflective of that Society or that
service or that business that we are
serving and I think that's a problem and
I think for people not to question that
is
problematic and and I've always thought
that corporations are part of society
there they're they're a subset of
society so it's important that there is
a kind of sync synchronization between
corporations and Society because it's
the same ecosystem right but that
synchronicity is really really important
they AB indate that responsibility to
have something that is you know that
that synchronicity with society that
kind of ear to the ground in terms of
trying to understand what is happening
around us from a societal point of view
from a political point of view why it's
important to have representation and not
representation for representation sake
of course but representation in terms of
actually having organizations that are
reflective of society actually having
different ways of thinking different
ways of being breaking patterns of
thinking that can be quite dominant and
actually quite limiting in terms of the
growth of an organization or trying to
engage different markets or different
types of individuals no I totally
totally concur with that and it's so
important from the business
standpoint but I think also from a pure
moral standpoint I think you know
sometimes I'm being asked why is that
important and I just answer you know
what because it's just the right thing
to do yeah period okay and then of
course are so many different aspects
behind that so what really surprised me
is when I was you know leading large
organizations or mentoring young people
I've noticed that the social Factor the
social origin is in fact very crucial
and so let me give you one example so
for example I remember I mentored a
young black female yeah very
talented and she came from a very
privileged background okay so she she
was raised in a very stable good family
loving family she went to the best
school the best Unis she and and it felt
to me that she didn't had most of the
issues of problems I was seeing with my
other mentees who didn't have those type
of environment sure and the reverse when
I mentored young white
professionals when they were coming from
an underprivileged social background
they tended to have the same issues than
the person of colors coming from another
prege background which which really
surprised me so it seems to be that
there is also a social pattern at play
here is that correct yeah I would say
yeah there is I mean what's always
interesting about you know if you take
class as an example it's a it's a
universal experience so lots of people
um live below the breadline and lots of
people would consider themselves because
class is a huge thing in the UK so it's
not something that translates in other
parts of Europe or outside of Europe but
if we just think about a domestic
context you know well over 70% of the
British population consider themselves
to be from a working-class background so
that's a significant 70% well over 70%
yeah so that that's significant
proportion and what I would say is that
those issues do translate because
they're kind of unilateral in that sense
you know um and again it comes back to
what I said about those inse sectional
factors that come into play um you know
class being one of those inse sections
which becomes hugely important in terms
of how people access to information that
access to information is almost like a
key um and it can be
determined by where you are in terms of
the types of capital you have so when
you spoke about the
um black young woman that you mentored
who you know was privately educated had
a really good education was from really
affluent
family that affluence that kind of
privilege it does provide a segue and
opportunities into
spaces that otherwise you know somebody
who doesn't have that type of social
capital or economic capital would
otherwise have but I would still present
the context for consideration that when
that individual walks into a room her
her status economically and and I guess
socially speaking is almost redundant
because the the premise of the the basis
of the judgment will still be around
that individual's race and regardless of
how much money someone has or doesn't
have or whatever kind of social
disposition they may be from in terms of
class or where they are on the kind of
ladder of Social and class justification
it doesn't it doesn't make any
difference in that sense because of how
prominent aspects of racial
discrimination are but it is a very
important thing to consider in terms of
how somebody is able to gain access to
information and that concept I wouldn't
say it's color blind but actually having
access and having
privilege it can be mobilized and
utilized in different many different
ways and I guess those who are fortunate
to have it it's about those individuals
recognizing that and recognizing some of
the
advantages that it affords them in terms
of being able to be socially mobile like
the individual you
described that's so interesting that's
so
interesting so let me um let me ask you
a completely different question so you
mentioned that at the very beginning you
mentioned that you you were helped at
moment of your
life and if I think of that I've been
really helped to and if I think of the
corporate world I've been tremendously
helped by senior leaders that most of
the time nearly always were white men
yeah sometimes white
women and I've seen in the corporate
world um I've seen people powerful
people helping helping young diverse
professionals could be gender could be
social origin could be ethnicity
whatever you know whatever okay I've
seen really people stepping in to help
but the kind of an individual you know
base on someone is helping someone
okay and again I would love to know what
what are your thoughts about that what's
the social human mechanism at play here
I I think the
I think the social and kind of human
mechanism at
play is an intrinsic one so there are
reasons why someone might extrinsically
want to help someone you know which are
often
material and there are reasons
intrinsically why somebody is motivated
to want to help someone and you know
there are people who are very fortunate
to meet people who are intrinsically
motivated to want to mentor and support
someone you've mentored and supported
many people in your career
and I'm sure there was no reward for
that I'm sure you did it because it came
from this place of actually I want to
give something back you know this
intervention Now is really about want
you wanting to give something back
that's an intrinsic motivation it's
nonprofit it's all of those things
and I think a big part of it is it's
from within it's from within so there
are things that motivate individuals to
want to give something back to
contribute or to create a space where
they see greater diversity or they see
people do well and that in of itself is
its own reward um and I guess as the
expression goes it's the gift that keeps
giving I guess the most important thing
is kind of some of the seeds you plant
in someone else you know how are they
watered how are they nourished because
fundamentally whatever you've done for
that individual you want that individual
to go and do for someone else so you
want it to continue to be kept being
played
forward um and I was very fortunate in
terms of the person I had or me who was
instrumental in that and their big thing
was look I don't need any fancy gifts I
don't need any big thanks but what I
what I do really need from you is
whatever I've done for you I need you to
do the same for someone else I need you
to mobilize that capitalize on it and
move it forward give it to someone else
and I often use this as an example
because I do actually genuinely believe
this
but the I believe the greatest sporting
franchise ever of the New Zealand All
Blacks and they have a particular turn
of phrase and Mai people and kind of
Polynesian and Pacific island people
that they're quite remarkable in terms
of how they connect with kind of the
earth their ancestry and all of these
types of things and kind of built within
their ancestry which is replicated in
this amazing formidable black Jersey
except the Jersey doesn't belong to you
your job is to take this jersey and to
put it in a better condition than you
found it so if Max Held a jersey for a
period of time the idea is that you
leave in as great condition as you can
find it for the next person to come and
take up the mantle and move that Jersey
on so the Jersey doesn't belong to you
and I guess it's recognizing this sense
of being able to or understanding that
at some point I will relinquish this
jersey but I want to leave it in as good
a state as possible you know um if I was
running a relay race and you know I want
to make sure that I've I've put the
person who's going to be in front of me
in the best position forward to drive
that home and I think you know there's
nothing that embodies that better in the
old black Jersey but a big part of that
is that that is a culture that is used a
lot in terms of mentoring you know it's
about giving someone this knowledge that
you've learned you've acquired you can't
read it in the book you can't pick it up
anywhere it's just this this kind of
tacit knowledge that one gains through
experience through touch and feel and
they're able to make sense of the world
around them and it's the kind of almost
internal wisdom that you pass on it's
it's a gift you pass it on to someone
else and you know the part of an ongoing
gift is that the individual who is the
inhabitant or the recipient of that gift
they then are able to give it on but by
the time they give it on they will have
acquired their own wisdoms and their own
knowledges and so it kind of builds and
it builds and it builds and I don't know
where it stops but it's not supposed to
stop but that's that's what I mean it's
something intrinsic it's something deep
within there are very few people I've
met in my life if any who engage in
mentoring as a process or supporting the
advancement of individuals for extrinsic
gain
it's always something internal
within that's my belief anyway no that
that's that resonates with me and I find
that very powerful very beautiful by the
way what you're saying here and so quite
recently
I've heard about a concept that really
surprised me like deeply surprised me so
we all know in the corporate world the
notion of the glass ceiling okay we all
know about that we all know what it is
and I think women demonstrate that
thanks God they can break the glass
ceiling we would like probably more but
they they're doing that and they've done
that and when it comes to of course
other type of diversities we would like
to see them breaking also the glass
ceiling okay we know that but the
concepts I discovered quite recently and
that really surprising me is the notion
of glass cleff and I must say I had
never heard about that so if I
understand well the IDE is that
especially people from minorities when
they come in position of power or large
responsibilities within the
corporations corporations will tend to
give
them super complex roles roles where
they could fail or well they have when
they have to completely you know
recover badly compromised situation okay
and so I was very surprised when I heard
that and I counted the role I've had
throughout my careers and which ones
were falling into this category of yeah
super dangerous rols recovering of
business units of businesses blah blah
and I will say I was completely
shocked
70% W 70% of my roles have been in those
categories and so forth wow that is
crazy so what's what's what's at play
here from your sociological perspective
I mean there's two things there's
there's an abdication of
responsibility um and creating a
situation because when we talk about
people shattering the glass ceiling it's
very important to kind of remember there
are some people who are allowed to be
unapologetically themselves in being
able to do that they're not incumbered
in any way you know there is not a there
is not a
deficit equation or approach applied to
their capabilities or their abilities so
there so we talk about Shing the glass
ceiling it's like okay well you know if
you're allowed to entirely be yourself
then yeah I think a lot of people can
shatter glass ceilings when they're
allowed to do that my belief is that
actually a lot of people um are not able
to be themselves entirely that's um and
a lot of that is because of the
discriminations that exist in the
workplace so there are things that they
have have to think about the way they
dress the way they conduct themselves
the way they speak their image the way
they all of these kind of things which
you know are stress in itself never mind
doing the job and then you get this kind
of situation where there are
opportunities that are kind of you know
vast in terms of again that blueprint
where can you know people go in an
organization and then you get these kind
of really narrow capped fenced
opportunities where one is in a contant
continuous state of having to prove
their eligibility to have one of these
kind of fancy roles in this bit you do
the troubleshooting and you fire you
firefight and you save this this
particular situation then there may be
this pot of gold on this side here but
this is an audition and your audition is
you need to competently put out this
fire
and that brings about a lot of stresses
a lot of pressure it's high
Jeopardy and there is very little margin
for eror working off the basis that
continuously a lot of black and ethnic
minority people in senior positions
particularly in these troubleshooting
positions there is there is already high
Jeopardy in those situations and there
is a questioning of their competence
it's almost kind of throwing them in the
deep sea and kind of seeing if they can
survive without a life jacket and
they're somehow supposed to find their
way to shore without a life jacket
oxygen
any Aid or assistance and if you're and
if you somehow manage to find yourself
at the shore you've been swept to the
Shore by some
miracle then you you you've passed a
test but this is the thing what ends up
happening is then you are perceived as
someone no they've done that they they
they've done it they they've done that
okay so do you know what we know that
they're reliable we can put them back in
that situation because the Rules of
Engagement
change and they do change for people of
color so that pot of gold that's
promised on that side actually know what
you've actually done is prove you are
capable of troubleshooting so your wings
are clipped you're seen as the
troubleshooter and the minute you could
be perfect for 99% of the time the one
time you falter is the one time you'll
be judged as being not as competent
inadequate not as good you don't have
the that deficit thinking starts coming
in they can't do it they can't do it you
give them these positions and they
struggle to do it but the truth is very
often those positions most people in
those positions have very little
resource or support around them to be
able to effectively do those jobs and
it's not like they're jobs that you know
people are jumping towards doing you
know but it's almost like that is your
audition you want to be part of this
club here this is how you need to
audition and very often it is black and
ethnic minority people that are placed
in those really volatile turbulent
situations one always terminal
situations and two they're hugely
unstable they're hugely unstable um so
you know if we're talking about equity
and fairness and giving someone an
opportunity to thrive I think there's a
big difference between thriving in an
organization and surviving an
organization and I think very often
individuals in those posts they're
surviving and what people don't always
consider is to
compromise psychologically physically
and mentally and how much is that part
of gold worth if one has to compromise
those Salient elements that are hugely
important in terms of just an individual
surviving the everyday throws of life um
and and so that there is a deep inequity
there because it's a one time one take
audition and it's like
right there's your audition go and if
you fall anything short of the
unreasonable expectations that are in
place you're deemed inadequate and
that's it you don't you don't get a re
audition and you know some people might
think that that sounds you know very
dramatic and and there's an exaggeration
there
but again I'll go back to what I said at
the beginning your eyes don't lie to you
if if that wasn't true why you know
there are many reasons why we don't see
diversity but that is one of them
because organizations can always point
to well actually that individual was
given an opportunity and they were un a
to perform but what were what was the
landscape and the conditions you gave to
the individual to be able to perform
their job what was what was available to
them what could their tentacles draw on
in terms of being able to competently do
their
job um and very often those that that
range of
movement is not there don't have the
same resources don't have the same
support don't have the same
infrastructure don't have the same teams
working um with them don't have the same
access to resources and those things
hugely clip the wings of the individual
who wants to progress through the
company because they're kind of like
well I don't have the same resources how
am I supposed to get the same outcomes
as my other counterparts in these
leadership positions when I don't
actually have the same resources you're
asking me to turn water into
wine well you know I need something to
be able to do that and in most cases
that that isn't the
case that's so powerful and and you
mentioned something
about the fact of being themselves so it
completely reminds me what you said
about you know the ability to be
ourselves to be who those person are
which and they are
different um which which is not that
easy in the corporate world right no I
think in organizations particularly big
organizations um there is a policing of
identity which is why I say who is
allowed
to belong who is allowed to be
themselves who is allowed to come into
work and wear trainers who is allowed to
wear who is allowed to go to work with
you know an an unironed shirt who's
allowed to wear a sport jacket instead
of wearing a suit you know um sport
jacket and jeans who's allowed who has
to wear you know these things they may
seem like trivial things to people on
the periphery but they're not because
that policing extends to many different
aspects how you look how you may wear
your hair um how you choose to present
yourself how you choose to speak you
know and there's almost for a lot of
black and ethnic minority people there's
this code twitching that has to happen
and this code twitching involves in some
respects stifling many aspects of their
personality of their being of their
person to be able to Traverse what are
really dominant you know white Workforce
spaces um and and and these kind of
things are hugely important because that
policing means that again it comes back
to who is allowed to truly beat himself
in the workplace because there is a tax
that comes when an individual isn't
truly able to be himself we know this
across the intersection in terms of you
know an individual who may have
disability if they're not able to be
seen and if you know reasonable
adjustments are not made for that
individual to thrive in the
workplace you know again it compromises
their ability to be themsel in their
full
kind of guys and these types of things
are are really really important you know
who is allowed to be who is allowed to
be unpoliced who is allowed who has to
who who ends up being policed you know
and that kind of
surveillance it's it's problematic and
it's difficult you know particularly
when you have individuals who are
encouraging someone to change how they
are to assimilate and when we talk about
assimilation what kind of ass we talking
about you know you know we talking about
assimilating to appear more palatable
and then you kind of drift into the
Realms of the palatable individual the
palatable black you know and I say that
and it's not to say that black people
you know should be seen in this
homogeneous way but it's just it's just
the idea that I can tell I could tell
somebody I think you need to dress more
like this or I think you need to look
more like this I don't think regardless
of race actually I don't think anybody
should be able to do that to anyone I
think people should be able to be the
truest forms of themsel but what has
historically happened is that in terms
of that truest form of
oneself it's black people and I think
minority people that have been policed
the most in terms of that authenticity
in terms of being their authentic selves
in the workplace which is why I make
reference specifically to um black and
ethnic minority people in this context
but again it's a concept that goes
across the intersection and can apply to
aspects of sexuality gender race
disability religion
Etc wow so we have some work to do we do
but it's it's incumbent upon all of us
to do that work um I think all to often
a lot of this work actually falls to um
women and in particular women of color
to mobilize um initiatives around
diversity in the workplace particularly
women of color and it's often
unenumerated and
unrecognized so I think it's incumbent
on all of us to be invested in this
charge and thinking about how we
disrupt dismantle interrogate these
spaces because it's it's to all our
benefit we all benefit from greater
equality and diversity in the workplace
everybody's a beneficiary of that and
and I've seen some initiatives in some
companies that I find absolutely awesome
so for example they completely review
the hiring or sourcing process um
started for example to work on CVS
without names without address things
like that you know just to to make it
more equal or even introducing during
the interview Loop you know members of
the companies that were themselves from
minorities or things like that you know
to create this connection and they
they're doing you know those small
things that trying to improve the
reality of of cor the corporations yeah
and I'm of the a firm belief that tiny
drops make a mighty ocean you know all
those little drops make a huge ocean and
and my wish and my dream and all of my
Endeavors have always worked towards
everybody being able to swim in this
ocean with life jackets um as opposed to
a few people being able to swim in this
ocean um and so those tiny drops that
you know everybody contributes to
creates this Mighty ocean for everyone
to feel like they can flourish and for
people to not feel like they're just
about keeping their head above water
water and then you know in in some cases
drowning you know you want everybody to
be kind of Treading Water pretty
comfortably and if they need a life
jacket it's there but actually they're
treading and they're absolutely fine but
you want everybody to have that
experience and that's where my Endeavors
have always been driven towards as a
yours you know you want everybody to
have that experience that that is
equality that is equity that is
diversity totally Jason we getting
closer to the to the end of this podcast
um I would like to ask you last question
so societies are what they are uh
corporations are what they are and
there's a lot of beautiful and powerful
and um wonderful things in societies and
in corporations lots of wonderful things
and I've been inside that world I've
I've benefited from that so I know how
yeah powerful and fulfilling it could be
also um so so if you were in front of a
young professional
from diverse
origin and you were to give one or two
key advice to this person to thrive and
to really be successful in the corporate
world and I know you're not in the
corporate world but I would love to hear
what would be your your your your your
piece of
advice that's a great question um so
someone that's not in the corporate
world but I guess I can try and think of
something that is kind of trans you know
can be translated into different
organizations and different kind of
stratospheres I think the most important
thing is to try and be as true to
yourself as possible I think um
Integrity is really important and I
think as I've got older I've probably
been slightly naive or or or a very
least Amazed by how often people are
willing to compromise their integrity to
progress in an organization but my
belief is that once you've done it once
you'll do it again and again and it's
not so much about getting to the top
wherever that vist may be it's about the
way you've done it and I think that's
really really important because to some
people Winning is Everything no matter
the cost but I don't believe that I
think there's a way to win and that way
to win particularly if you're from an
underrepresented background becomes a
really good blueprint in terms of how to
advise somebody about how they can win
this is the way to do it because there a
way to do it I think humility is
everything I think if you're good I
don't think you need to tell people how
good you are it doesn't matter what
organization anyone Works in I truly
truly truly believe that there are times
where you have to advocate for yourself
and you have to you know make it very
clear what you have done and why you are
a valuable asset to an organization and
that is important it's very different
from being an empty Barrel making the
most
noise um so I think humity is hugely
important I also think it provides an
Exemplar that you know you can be
successful and you can carry yourself in
a particular way and I think the one
other piece of advice I would give is
whatever you do take great pride in it
you know I was very fortunate to have
cleaning jobs a lot of those buildings
the cleaning the cleaning aspect of
those buildings cleaning those buildings
often starts between kind of 4: and 7:00
a.m. and in another lifetime not that
long ago um I had cleaning jobs to try
and make end meet and the one thing that
I never ever forgot was how much pride
people took in those jobs in terms of
how well they did it and their attention
to
detail and there's a colleague of mine
that I I met and she also used to have a
cleaning job and she once said to me
that you know Jason every day in that
job I wore a suit wore a suit in that
job he said I wore a suit because I not
only did I take pride in what I did but
I thought I'm going to work I'm going to
wear this suit every day as a reminder
to me what I am eventually working
towards now that individual is a very
big Cog now in a very very big machine
um but that story really struck aord
with me because her whole thing was it's
so important to take pride in whatever
you do um and having that attitude I
think is a really Universal attitude
towards whatever you do in life just
taking pride in what you do and
always having this belief that there is
something much more important and bigger
than yourself so where possible in any
organization how can you uplift those
how can you uplift anybody if that can
be the central premise of your practice
in an organization then I think you're
on a good footing it is about how you
advocate for other people how you create
space for other people and most
importantly um I think it's a really
underrated thing being nice it costs
nothing to be nice honestly like I
always tell people it's very expensive
to be rude and to be disrespectful and I
always think there's this
whole kind of Ideal that you've got to
be a certain way to progress you know
nice guys or nice people finish last I I
don't understand who comes up with these
things I think being nice is its own
reward doesn't need to be an extrinsic
reward that comes from that or some V
capitalist Venture that comes from that
it's actually whether someone was or
they wasn't just being a nice person
will actually take you a lot further in
life because what it does mean if you're
working in a huge organization is that
actually if you're nice that person that
is working for you they might go that
extra intro mile on the basis that
actually you know what that person's
been so good to me and they're so nice
that I will I will do that extra hour
for them I will do that extra activity
they have asked me do I will push myself
a little bit further than I would
normally do because Max asked me to do
it and because he's been so good to me
that's and that you know it's not that
you give to receive but it's this idea
of being nice has always been and will
always be no matter what anybody says
its own
reward so Jason thank you for this
wonderful conversation really appreciate
your time I know you have a crazy agenda
so I really appreciate that there's a
lot of Food For Thoughts in what you
said so I will really think of that and
I hope our audience will also benefit
from that and think about that so thank
you so much J no Max the privilege has
been on mine and honestly continue this
amazing work and it's just I feel very
very fortunate to have broken bread with
you today so thank you so so much thanks
really appreciate thank you